<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Post on Karstens Lab</title>
    <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Post on Karstens Lab</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="http://karstenslab.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Congrats to Kate for receiving the Frictionless data fellowship!</title>
      <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/frictionlessfellow/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/frictionlessfellow/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do you see what I see? Introducing microshades: An R package for improving color accessibility and organization of complex data</title>
      <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/microshades/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/microshades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Approximately 300 million people in the world have Color Vision Deficiency (CVD), which is comparable to the most recent estimate of the US population. Individuals with CVD do not experience a complete loss of color vision, though the ability to distinguish different colors is reduced.  When creating  figures and graphics that use color, it is important to consider that people with CVD will interact with this material, and may not perceive all of the information tied to the colors correctly.  There are multiple CVD friendly color palettes available on R to apply to visuals, however they are restricted to 8 different colors.  When working with complex data, such as microbiome data, this is insufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To overcome this limitation, we developed the microshades R package to provide custom color shading palettes that improve accessibility and data organization. Each color palette contains six base colors with five incremental light to dark shades, for a total of 30 available colors per palette type that can be directly applied to any plot. This package includes two crafted color palettes,  microshades_cvd_palettes and microshades_palettes.   The microshades_cvd_palettes contain colors that are universally CVD friendly. The individual microshades_palettes are CVD friendly, but when used in conjunction with multiple microshades_palettes, are not universally accessible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to color palettes, the microshades package contains functions to aid in data visualization including functions for creating stacked bar plots organized by a data-driven hierarchy. The microshades package can be used in conjunction with common microbiome R packages, such as phyloseq, to enhance microbiome data visualization. In the case of microbiome data, the base colors correspond with a higher order taxonomic group (e.g. phylum) and shades of the base color represent subgroups of the taxonomic group (e.g. genus). Subgroup shading is determined by the abundance in the dataset. Darker shades indicate the most abundant subgroup for each group, and lighter shades represent less abundant subgroups. To further assist users with data storytelling, we have functions to sort data both vertically and horizontally based on ranked abundance or user specification.  The accessibility and advanced color organization features described help data reviewers and consumers notice visual patterns and trends easier. Examples of microshades in action are available on our website, for both microbiome and other datasets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://karstenslab.github.io/microshades&#34;&gt;https://karstenslab.github.io/microshades&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congrats to 2020 Graduates!</title>
      <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/2020-grads/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/2020-grads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;2020 has been hard in so many ways, BUT the Karstens lab members have been busy wrapping up their studies. DMICE BCBC Masters students Carter Hoffman and Alfonso Poire completed their programs. Carter’s thesis focused on identifying species-level information from 16S rRNA gene sequencing data. Alfonso completed a capstone/internship at J Craig Venter Institute probing molecular interactions in the nitrogen-fixing cyanobacteria-feather moss symbiosis. Also, our first EXITO scholar, Fatoumata Jallow, graduated! Her EXITO project explored using additional experimental information to improve urinary microbiome measurements. Finally, urogynecology Fellow Ian Fields, MD completed his training and will be joining OHSU as faculty.    We are sad that were not able to celebrate these accomplishments in person! CONGRATS ALL!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congrats to 2018 graduates!</title>
      <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/2018-grads/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/2018-grads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first two graduate students in the Karstens lab have officially graduated! Mark Klick and Vincent Caruso joined the Karstens Lab to complete their Master’s thesis project in 2017. Mark’s project was in collaboration with the Asquith Lab and focused on investigating a novel IgA Seq technology to understand spondyloarthritis. He will be joining this lab as a Research Assistant after graduation. Vincent’s project focused on benchmarking newly developed microbiome bioinformatic approachesin samples of varying microbial biomass. He will be completing a Fellowship at the CDC. Congrats Mark and Vincent!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
