<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Post on Karstens Lab</title>
    <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Post on Karstens Lab</description>
    <generator>Source Themes academia (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Copyright &amp;copy; {year}</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	    <atom:link href="http://karstenslab.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Do you see what I see? </title>
      <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/microshades/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/microshades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We are excited to share the microshades R package we have designed to provide custom color shading palettes for improving accessibility and data organization. Approximately 300 million people in the world have Color Vision Deficiency (CVD), so it is important to consider CVD accessibility when creating scientific figures that use color to relay information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This package includes color palettes, containing 6 base colors with 5 incremental light to dark shades, for a total of 30 available colors per palette type that can be directly applied to any plot. In addition to color palettes, this package can also be used in conjunction with the R package phyloseq to enhance microbiome data visualization. The accessibility and advanced color organization features help data reviewers and consumers notice visual patterns and trends easier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visit our &lt;a href=&#34;https://karstenslab.github.io/microshades&#34;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; to learn more!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Color Vision Deficency Resources</title>
      <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/cvd_resources/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/cvd_resources/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Build EXITO student Emory Neer has developed a resource page for CVD friendliness resources. She has worked on handcrafting a universially accessible palette  that is avalible the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.google.com/pdx.edu/cvd-friendliness-resources/home?fbclid=IwAR01_rPpeWNK3GaI2ozpnJr7THLH1ooWU7ZJ98ixVPJc2dBc18OEf_Mo-Mo&#34;&gt;resources page&lt;/a&gt;. Also avalible at bit.ly/cvdresources&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congrats to Kate for receiving the Frictionless data fellowship!</title>
      <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/frictionlessfellow/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/frictionlessfellow/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Learn more about &lt;a href=&#34;https://frictionlessdata.io&#34;&gt;Frictionless Data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congrats to 2020 Graduates!</title>
      <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/2020-grads/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/2020-grads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;2020 has been hard in so many ways, BUT the Karstens lab members have been busy wrapping up their studies. DMICE BCBC Masters students Carter Hoffman and Alfonso Poire completed their programs. Carter’s thesis focused on identifying species-level information from 16S rRNA gene sequencing data. Alfonso completed a capstone/internship at J Craig Venter Institute probing molecular interactions in the nitrogen-fixing cyanobacteria-feather moss symbiosis. Also, our first EXITO scholar, Fatoumata Jallow, graduated! Her EXITO project explored using additional experimental information to improve urinary microbiome measurements. Finally, urogynecology Fellow Ian Fields, MD completed his training and will be joining OHSU as faculty.    We are sad that were not able to celebrate these accomplishments in person! CONGRATS ALL!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Congrats to 2018 graduates!</title>
      <link>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/2018-grads/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://karstenslab.github.io/post/2018-grads/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The first two graduate students in the Karstens lab have officially graduated! Mark Klick and Vincent Caruso joined the Karstens Lab to complete their Master’s thesis project in 2017. Mark’s project was in collaboration with the Asquith Lab and focused on investigating a novel IgA Seq technology to understand spondyloarthritis. He will be joining this lab as a Research Assistant after graduation. Vincent’s project focused on benchmarking newly developed microbiome bioinformatic approachesin samples of varying microbial biomass. He will be completing a Fellowship at the CDC. Congrats Mark and Vincent!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
